<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<resources>
    <string name="app_name">CBT-i Coach</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_2">coach</string>
    <string name="title_10b">Software End User License Agreement</string>
    <string name="s_Continue">Continue</string>
    <string name="title_10d">Welcome to CBT-i Coach</string>
    <string name="s_coach">coach</string>
    <string name="s_IAccept">I Accept</string>
    <string name="s_CBTi">CBT-i</string>
    <string name="s_dva">United States Department \nof Veterans Affairs (\"VA\")</string>
    <string name="welcome_10d">Welcome to Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia (CBT-i) Coach, a mobile companion for in-person therapy for promoting better sleep.\n\nCBT-i Coach does not replace professional treatment.  Let your healthcare provider know if you are using CBT-i Coach.</string>
    <string name="sleepprescription">Sleep Prescription</string>
    <string name="sleepprescriptionnote">Your Sleep Prescription will appear here once you have completed 5 sleep day diaries</string>
    <string name="sleeppwaketime">Wake Time</string>
    <string name="sleeppefficiency">Efficiency</string>
    <string name="sleeppbedtime">Bedtime</string>
    <string name="s_Help">Help</string>
    <string name="s_Reminders">Reminders</string>
    <string name="s_About">About</string>
    <string name="s_Learn">Learn</string>
    <string name="s_Tools">Tools</string>
    <string name="s_MySleep">My Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_Home">Home</string>
    <string name="s_updatesleepprescription">Update Sleep Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_UpdateSleep">Update Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_Assessment">Assessment</string>
    <string name="s_MySleepHelp">Record sleep habits and help with keeping a sleep schedule</string>
    <string name="s_ToolsHelp">Ways to prepare for sleep and quiet your mind</string>
    <string name="s_LearnHelp">View information about sleep</string>
    <string name="s_RemindersHelp">Stick to a healthy sleep schedule</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectPartners">Project Partners</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectTeam">Project Team</string>
    <string name="s_Settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="s_ScheduleAssessments">Schedule Assessments</string>
    <string name="s_TakeAssessment">Take Assessment</string>
    <string name="s_ResultsHistory">Results History</string>
    <string name="s_SleepPrescription">Sleep Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_INeedMoreSleep">I Need More Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_NeedSleep">Need Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_31bhelp">Use this assessment, the Insomnia Severity Index, to get a sense of your insomnia symptoms over time. It is recommended that you do not take this assessment more than once per week.</string>
    <string name="s_32ehelp">This graph shows how your scores on the assessment have changed over time. It is normal for your symptoms to go up and down a bit from week to week.  Higher scores mean that you have more severe symptoms, so if your line is going up, you may want to check in with your provider and let him or her know (or get a provider if you don\'t already have one).</string>
    <string name="s_21b44">If your sleep or daytime functioning is affected by some unusual event (such as an illness, or an emergency) you may make brief notes on your diary.</string>
    <string name="s_21b33"> If you remember your sleep habits for that day, you can edit the diary through the "Past Diaries" tab. Otherwise leave it blank.</string>
    <string name="s_21b5">•	What do the words "bed" and "day" mean on the diary? </string>
    <string name="s_21b6">•	Will answering these questions about my sleep keep me awake?</string>
    <string name="s_21b3">•	What should I do if I miss a day?</string>
    <string name="s_21b4">•	What if something unusual affects my sleep or how I feel in the daytime? </string>
    <string name="s_21b1">•	What is a Sleep Diary? </string>
    <string name="s_21b2">•	How often and when do I fill out the sleep diary? </string>
    <string name="s_21b22">It is necessary for you to complete your sleep diary every day. Remember, you will generally be answering questions about your sleep habits during the previous day and night. If possible, the sleep diary should be completed within one hour of getting out of bed in the morning.</string>
    <string name="s_21b66">This is not usually a problem. You should not worry about giving exact times, and you should not watch the clock. Just give your best estimate.</string>
    <string name="s_21b11">A sleep diary is designed to gather information about your daily sleep pattern.  It should be filled out every day and is designed to be completed within two hours of getting out of bed in the morning.  If you forget to fill in the diary or are unable to finish it, leave the diary blank for that day.</string>
    <string name="s_21b55">This diary can be used for people who are awake or asleep at unusual times. In the sleep diary, the word \‘day\' is the time when you choose or are required to be awake. The term "bed" means the place where you usually sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_SleepDiary">Sleep Diary</string>
    <string name="s_PastWeeks">Past 7 days Sleep Diary completion: </string>
    <string name="s_SleepDiaryReminder">Sleep Diary Reminder</string>
    <string name="s_RecommendedDaily">Recommended Daily</string>
    <string name="s_Time">Time</string>
    <string name="s_51a">CBT-i Coach is a mobile phone application for Veterans, Service Members, and others who are participating in Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia.  It is intended to augment face-to-face care with a healthcare professional.  You can also use it on its own, but it is not intended to replace therapy for those who need it.\nIt will guide you through the process of learning about sleep, developing good sleep habits, and getting rid of habits that interfere with sleep.  It also provides a structured program to get your biological clock reset to make it easier to go to sleep and to sleep through the night.</string>
    <string name="s_ResetAllUserData">Reset All User Data</string>
    <string name="s_ProvideAUD">Provide Anonymous Usage Data</string>
    <string name="s_50b">Help improve this application by automatically sending daily diagnostics and usage data.  Diagnostic data may include location information.   Although no one can see your personal data, looking at overall trends helps us make better products. </string>
    <string name="s_PTeam">•	Julia E. Hoffman, Psy.D.\n•	Katherine Taylor, M.P.H.\n•	Eric Kuhn, Ph.D.\n•	Carolyn Greene, Ph.D.\n•	Kenneth Weingardt, Ph.D.\n•	Josef I. Ruzek, Ph.D.</string>
    <string name="s_SME">Subject Matter Experts</string>
    <string name="s_SMETeam">•	Rachel Manber, Ph.D.\n•	Mickey Trockel, M.D.\n•	Philip Gehrman, Ph.D.</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectPartners1">CBT-i Coach was a collaborative effort between VA’s National Center for PTSD, Stanford University Medical Center, and DoD’s National Center for Telehealth and Technology.\nCBT-i Coach is based on the therapy manual, Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia in Veterans, by Rachel Manber, Ph.D., Leah Friedman, Ph.D., Colleen Carney, Ph.D., Jack Edinger, Ph.D., Dana Epstein, Ph.D., Patricia Haynes, Ph.D., Wilfred Pigeon, Ph.D. and Allison Siebern, Ph.D.  CBT-i has been shown to be efficacious for insomnia for both Veterans and civilians.</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectPartners4">The VA Sierra Pacific Mental Illness Research, Education, and Clinical Center is building an integrated system of clinical, research, and educational efforts designed to improve the clinical care for Veterans with dementia and with PTSD both in VISN 21 and system-wide.</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectPartners3">Stanford School of Medicine\'s mission is to be a premier research-intensive medical school that improves health through leadership and a collaborative approach to discovery and innovation in patient care, education, and research.</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectPartners5">The National Center for Telehealth and Technology |T2| researches, develops, evaluates, and deploys new and existing technologies for Psychological Health (PH) and Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI) across the Department of Defense (DoD). \nT2 is a component center of the Defense Centers of Excellence for Psychological Health and Traumatic Brain Injury (DCoE).\n\n\t"Technology to Make People Healthy"\n\nFor more information about insomnia and other topics for Veterans, see http://ptsd.va.gov.</string>
    <string name="s_ProjectPartners2">The National Center for PTSD, within the Department of Veterans Affairs, aims to help U.S. Veterans and others through research, education, and training on trauma and PTSD.\n\"Advancing Science and Promoting Understanding of Traumatic Stress\"
</string>
    <string name="s_40b">Read about how your sleep functioning, sleep environment and daily habits can affect your health. Find definitions for terms used in cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia.</string>
    <string name="s_CBTiGlossary">CBT-i Glossary</string>
    <string name="s_HealthySleepHabits">Healthy Sleep Habits</string>
    <string name="s_Sleep101">Sleep 101</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_1">CBT-i - Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia - is a non-medication treatment of insomnia that is based on scientific knowledge about sleep.  The goals of CBT-i are to help you fall asleep, stay asleep, and improve your daytime functioning as a result of better sleep at night. \n\n\t•	The "cognitive" part of CBT-i focuses on thoughts, feelings, and expectations about sleep and insomnia that may stand in the way of good sleep. \n\t•	The "behavioral" aspect of CBT-i helps people adopt personal sleep habits that, based on the science of sleep, will help them sleep better. 
</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_1t">What is CBT-i?</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_2t">Why Do We Sleep?</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_2">Sleep, like oxygen, food and water, is one of our basic daily needs. Sleep scientists disagree on the fundamental biological purpose of sleep. Some believe that during sleep the human body restores and repairs cells and tissues that have been damaged while we are awake. Other experts believe that sleep is essential to the maintenance of normal human metabolism. There is also evidence that sleep is important for storing memories.  Despite these differences, sleep experts generally agree that to function best we all require consistent, good quality sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_3">Many research studies have shown that sleep is a process made up of two states: Rapid Eye Movement (REM sleep) and Non-Rapid Eye Movement (non REM) sleep. Non REM sleep is composed of several stages, and occupies about 75- 80% of the night\'s sleep of a \"typical\" young, healthy adult. The rest of the night\’s sleep is REM sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_3t">The Stages of Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_32">N1:  People experience stage N1 sleep as very light; when awakened, many individuals think they have not been asleep. Nonetheless, stage N1 seems to be an essential part of normal sleep. People with insomnia and older adults spend more of their night\’s sleep in stage N1 than those without insomnia.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_33">N2:  N2 occupies about 40-55% of the night\'s sleep in a young adult.  It is harder to wake a person from this stage and most people know they have been asleep. </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_34">N3:  Brain activity during N3 sleep is also called slow-wave sleep because it is characterized by slow, distinctive waves called Delta waves.  N3 is perceived as the deepest sleep; it is hardest to wake people up from this stage.  People tend to have more stage N3 sleep on nights following prolonged wakefulness.  </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_35">REM:  REM sleep is when most dreaming occurs. During REM sleep, bursts of rapid eye movements can be observed and heart and breathing rates become less regular. There is increased blood flow to the brain. Interestingly, brain wave activities during REM sleep are a bit similar to those seen during wakefulness. However, during REM sleep the body\'s skeletal muscles are in a state of relative paralysis which prevents people from \'acting out\' their dreams</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_42">Sleep Drive:  Our sleep drive is lowest in the morning and gradually increases as the day progresses. Sleeping gradually reduces our sleep drive as we "recharge our energy reserve", which is why napping close to bedtime (for example, dozing off while watching TV in the evening) can make it harder for us to fall asleep later.  The longer the time that has elapsed since we last slept, the stronger is the sleep drive  and the easier it will be to fall asleep. When the sleep drive is very strong we feel sleepy.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_43">Circadian Process:  People have powerful internal \‘clocks\’ that affect their bodily functioning, including digestion, body temperature, and sleep/wake pattern. Most of these \'clocks\' seem to work across roughly 24-hour periods. Irregular sleep schedules weaken our biological clocks, which is why it is particularly important to keep regular wake and out of bed times.  Our clocks use light signals to reset, so getting out of bed at the same time each day keeps the clock ticking with a strong and regular beat, which supports good sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_44">Arousal:  Feeling \"on guard\" or anxious can mask sleepiness (strong sleep drive) and make sleep difficult. For example, when a sleep-deprived person is anxious about having to appear before a traffic judge, this person generally does not feel sleepy at the hearing despite not getting enough sleep the night before. When the court appearance is over, and the person is relaxed, he may nod off while reading a magazine article because his strong sleep drive is no longer masked by anxiety. This example demonstrates how the balance of sleep drive and arousal (such as a perceived threat, anxiety, active mind, or body tension) determines the likelihood of sleep at a given time. Common sources of arousal at bedtime include thinking about issues that have not been adequately resolved or addressed during the day, worrying about sleep, trying to remember what needs to be done the next day, and worrying about things not in one\’s control.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_4">There are two processes that regulate sleep and wakefulness, the sleep drive and the circadian process. Arousal also affects our ability to sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_4t">Sleep Regulators</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_5t">Sleepiness vs. Tiredness</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_5">Often people use the terms \"sleepy\" and \"tired\" interchangeably, but they actually mean different things. \"Tired\" can mean that the person has low energy, but not necessarily a need to sleep. \"Sleepy\" generally refers to an actual need for sleep. Thinking about your levels of feeling tired and sleepy separately might help you determine when you have an actual need for sleep (strong sleep drive), rather than an overall lack of energy. This can help you decide when to actually try to sleep and when to rest your body.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_6">Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) describes a group of symptoms that occur in response to a traumatic event such as being involved in an automobile accident or military combat. These symptoms include feeling tense or \"on guard\" much of the time, having flashbacks or nightmares and feeling disconnected from people and situations. Trouble sleeping is an extremely common symptom of PTSD.\n\nSome individuals report avoiding sleeping because they are afraid they might have nightmares, or they may not be able to respond to urgent situations that might arise. They might engage in \"safety behaviors\", such as listening for noises outside or checking locks on doors and windows. People with PTSD may prefer sleeping in locations other than the bedroom or try to delay bedtime. Sleep can also be hard if it brings back memories of trauma, for example, if the trauma happened at night.    </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_6t">PTSD and Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_9t">Depression and Sleep </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_7t">Nightmares</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_10t">Sleep Apnea </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_9">Most people with depression have trouble sleeping.  Some wake up earlier than desired or planned and others may find it difficult to get out of bed because they do not derive much pleasure from what they do during the day.  The good news is that CBT-i is effective even for people who experience depression. Improved sleep can improve  mood</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_8">Because sleep deprivation can cause confusion when awakened suddenly, it is dangerous to keep weapons within easy access. Being confused and frightened upon waking will increase the likelihood of misjudging the situation and unintentionally discharging a loaded weapon. Therefore, it’s important to lock up or unload weapons at home even if doing so increases the sense of vulnerability and anxiety, which can lead to sleeplessness in the short run.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_7">Nightmares are bad dreams that cause awakening and strong negative emotional responses like fear upon waking up from the dream. For veterans, many nightmares relate to dangerous combat activities. Awakening after a nightmare can result in people replaying the nightmare, trying to figure out why the nightmare happened and what it might mean.  Some experts believe that by avoiding sleeping and replaying nightmares people may be more likely to have future nightmares. </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_8t">Weapons and Sleep  </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_10">Sleep apnea is a sleep disorder in which the airway passages (nose or throat) are fully or partially obstructed.  These events can lead to a decrease in oxygen levels in the blood and awakenings. Nighttime symptoms of sleep apnea include loud snoring, snorting, and gasping for air.  Unless told by a partner, many people have no idea they have these symptoms of sleep apnea.  Daytime symptoms of sleep apnea include feeling tired in the morning and sleepy during the day. Other daytime symptoms include a morning headache that resolves shortly after rising and waking with a dry mouth.  If you experience these symptoms on a regular basis you should talk to your doctor. Sleep apnea increases the risk of heart disease and stroke.</string>
    <string name="s_learn101_11">Certain medications and commonly used substances can disrupt sleep. These include some asthma medications (e.g. theophylline), some over the counter  decongestants and allergy and cold medicines, some steroids (e.g., prednisone), beta blockers (medicines used to treat heart conditions), medications for ADHD (e.g., Adderall) and some antidepressants (e.g., Wellbutrin). Ask your physician if any medications you are taking might interfere with sleep.  Don\’t stop taking prescribed medications without first checking with your doctor.\n\nWhile \"sleeping pills\" are  useful  when taken for a short time , prolonged, chronic use can cause tolerance (needing more medication to get the same effect) and psychological dependence. Each person has a different level of tolerance for these medications and will have a different reaction to their use. Some experience the effect of the medication for a long time and are sleepy or lethargic the next day. Make sure to only use sleep medications as instructed by your physician and to report any side effects to your treatment team. </string>
    <string name="s_learn101_11t">Medications</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_01">Preoccupation with small and big worries, mulling over your problems, or planning future events while in bed can keep you awake.  When disruptive thinking occurs frequently, you may find it helpful to set aside a time each day to do the thinking, worrying, problem-solving, and planning you need to do. Then, if intrusive thoughts occur during your sleep period, postpone them to the \"thinking and worrying time\" during the next day. By scheduling a daily time to focus on your concerns you will find that you are having fewer worried thoughts while you are in bed.  For help with his, see \"Scheduling a Worry Time\" in the \"Tools\" tab.\n\n
Many people find themselves worrying about not sleeping, which, unfortunately, can also keep them awake. Remember that, while not sleeping can be uncomfortable, your body is designed to tolerate less-than-perfect sleep some nights. In fact, losing sleep can increase your sleep drive, which may result in improved sleep the following nights. It’s important to reduce night time anxiety in order to improve your chances of getting quality sleep. 
</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_01t">Worrying in Bed</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_04">You can create a \"buffer zone\" for yourself, which is a quiet time right before bedtime that allows you to wind down. It provides a transition between activities of the day and the quiet, more peaceful time of sleep. Shedding the day’s excitements and tensions will calm you and allow sleep to unfold naturally. For ideas about ways to create a buffer zone, see the \"Tools\" tab.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_02">Being aware of the time can increase frustration and interfere with sleep.  Put your clock across the room, turn it around, and do not check the time in the middle of the night.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_03">Sleeping at times other than your specified time in bed can weaken your sleep drive and could throw off the natural circadian rhythm of your body.  However, if you find yourself feeling very sleepy (not just tired, but actually sleepy) you can take a brief (15 to 30 minutes) nap. Sleepy people make mistakes, misjudge situations, and may accidently hurt themselves or others. Therefore, do not try and stay awake just to keep in line with your sleep prescription. Safety supersedes all other sleep guidelines.\n\n If you feel like you have to nap, try to do it 7 to 9 hours after your morning wake up time, which for most people is in the mid-afternoon.  The nap will then coincide with the pattern of your biological clock, which has a natural dip (lower alertness) at that time. Ideally naps should be taken at approximately the same time every day, otherwise they may weaken your sleep signal. Naps should be taken in your bed because you are training yourself to associate the bed with sleep. Set your alarm so you don\’t nap too long. </string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_02t">Watching the Clock</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_03t">Napping</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_04t">Winding Down</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_10">Nicotine leaves the body fairly quickly, usually about two hours after use. This can create cravings in the middle of the night. For this reason it is best to avoid smoking at least two hours before bedtime, if possible.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_11">Your sleep environment needs to be quiet, dark, and safe with a comfortable temperature. Noise and light (even dim light) may interrupt or shorten your sleep. One good way to filter out unwanted noise is to sleep with  \"white noise\" in the background. This can be the sound of a fan, the hum of static on the radio, or you can purchase a \"white noise\" machine to help with sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_10t">Nicotine Use</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_05t">Using the Bedroom for Two Activities Only</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_06t">Eating</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_11t">Getting Comfortable</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_07t">Caffeine Use</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_08">Exercise too close to bedtime may have a negative impact on sleep. Exercise activates the body, and raises the core body temperature, which doesn’t allow the body to experience its normal drop in temperature prior to sleep. Strenuous exercise should be avoided about four hours before bedtime.  Gentle stretching exercises before bedtime are OK and may even be relaxing.  </string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_09">Alcoholic beverages can be relaxing and make people feel drowsy, however they can have the opposite effect later in the night. As alcohol is metabolized, it leads to restless and disturbed sleep. For most people with no history of alcoholism, one glass of wine or beer with dinner scheduled 3-4 hours before bedtime is not likely to have a negative impact on sleep. However, for some very sensitive individuals complete elimination of alcohol in the evening may be advisable.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_06">The process of falling asleep slows down the digestive system.  A heavy meal close to bedtime may therefore lead to indigestion or reflux during the night, both of which disturb sleep.  Allowing a 4 hour window between eating and sleeping to let food to digest is a good sleep practice. However if you are hungry, a light snack is appropriate. </string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_07">Caffeine is a relatively long-acting stimulant whose effects may last for several hours after it is consumed. People differ greatly in how caffeine affects them and in the length of time it lasts, for example, older adults tend to be more sensitive to caffeine. Caffeine can remain active 4-5 hours after it is consumed, so try to avoid having caffeine after lunch if you want to make sure it doesn’t affect your sleep. Limit consumption of caffeinated beverages to the equivalent of no more than three, eight- ounce cups daily.  To set goals for caffeine use, check out the \"Tools\" tab.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_05">While in bed, you should avoid doing things that you do when you are awake. Do not read, watch TV, eat, study or use your phone or laptop. Doing these things in bed creates associations between the bed and activities other than sleep, which can train your mind to stay awake while in bed. By only using your bed for sleep, you can help it become a place where sleep comes naturally.  Sexual activity is the only exception to this guideline.\n\nThe most important activity that you should eliminate from the bed is the activity of \"trying to sleep\" because it inevitably interferes with the natural sleep process. If you find yourself thinking about sleep while in bed, get up. It can be hard not to use your bed for other things, especially if you live in a studio apartment or a dorm room, but it can be an important part of improving your sleep habits.</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_08t">Exercise</string>
    <string name="s_learnsh_09t">Alcohol Use</string>
    <string name="s_glossary07t">Sleepy</string>
    <string name="s_glossary06t">Bed</string>
    <string name="s_glossary08t">Tired</string>
    <string name="s_glossary01t">Sleep Diary</string>
    <string name="s_glossary03t">Sleep Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_glossary02t">Sleep Efficiency</string>
    <string name="s_glossary05t">Total Sleep Time</string>
    <string name="s_glossary08">Feeling an overall lack of energy or general fatigue.</string>
    <string name="s_glossary06">Bed, in the context of this app, means any place designated for sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_glossary07">Feeling a need for sleep (compare to a feeling of "tiredness").</string>
    <string name="s_glossary05">Total Sleep Time:  The actual amount of sleep you get during a sleep period.  It’s equal to total sleep period minus awake time.</string>
    <string name="s_glossary04">Time in Bed is the amount of recommended time to be in bed.  It is determined by taking the recommended awake time minus bed time.</string>
    <string name="s_glossary03">Going to bed and waking up at the same times each day can help strengthen the natural cues from your internal biological sleep clock. This is part of the reason sleep therapists recommend a sleep prescription, a set bedtime and set wake time, for people who are having sleep difficulties</string>
    <string name="s_glossary02">Your sleep efficiency is the proportion of the time you spend asleep relative to the time you spend in bed.  For example, if you sleep for 4 hours out of the 6 hours you are in bed, your sleep efficiency is 4/6 or 66.6%.  The formula is for sleep efficiency is:  average sleep efficiency = average total sleep time / average time in bed</string>
    <string name="s_glossary01">A sleep diary is designed to gather information about your daily sleep pattern.  It should be filled out every day and is designed to be completed within two hours of getting out of bed in the morning.  If you forget to fill in the diary or are unable to finish it, leave the diary blank for that day.</string>
    <string name="s_glossary04t">Time in Bed</string>
    <string name="s_WorryTime">Worry Time</string>
    <string name="s_WindDownTime">Wind Down Time</string>
    <string name="s_StopCaffeine">Stop Caffeine</string>
    <string name="s_PrescribedBedtime">Prescribed Bedtime</string>
    <string name="s_PrescribedWakeTime">Prescribed Wake Time</string>
    <string name="s_60d">Use these reminders to help you keep a healthy sleep schedule and to encourage you to use the tools in this app.</string>
    <string name="s_UpdateSleepPrescription">Update Sleep Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_remPrescribedWake">Prescribed Wake Time</string>
    <string name="s_remSleepDiary">Complete Sleep Diary</string>
    <string name="s_remPrescribedBedtime">Prescribed Bedtime</string>
    <string name="s_remWindDown">Begin Wind Down Time</string>
    <string name="s_Reminder">Reminder</string>
    <string name="s_remUpdateSleepPrescription">Update Sleep Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_remUpdateSleepPrescriptionText">It has been one week since you updated your sleep prescription. It may be helpful to review your prescribed bedtime and wake time with your provider or calculate a new sleep prescription. You can change your prescribed bedtime and wake time under \"Update Prescription.\"</string>
    <string name="s_remSleepDiaryReminderHint">It is recommended to fill out sleep diaries within two hours of your scheduled wake up time, and should be completed every day. </string>
    <string name="s_remTakeAssessment">Take Assessment</string>
    <string name="s_remTakeAssessmentText">Take Assessment</string>
    <string name="s_remWorryTime">Worry Time</string>
    <string name="s_remStopCaffeine">Stop Caffeine</string>
    <string name="s_ResetAllReminders">Reset All Reminders</string>
    <string name="s_ResetReminbersComplete">Reset Reminders Complete</string>
    <string name="s_QuietYourMind">Quiet Your Mind</string>
    <string name="s_PreventInsomniaintheFuture">Prevent Insomnia in the Future</string>
    <string name="s_CreateNewSleepHabits">Create New Sleep Habits</string>
    <string name="s_30b">This section provides interactive modules that can help you develop and maintain helpful sleep habits and relax and ready your body for sleep. You can also use this section to learn about how to continue to have positive sleep habits in the future.</string>
    <string name="s_34b">Using CBT-i guidelines can help create a schedule and environment that helps you sleep. Use this \"Build New Sleep Habits\" section to implement some changes in your routine. If you are looking for ways to quiet your mind, try some of the activities under the \"Quiet Your Mind\" tab.</string>
    <string name="s_34e">Staying awake until you are truly sleepy can help strengthen your sleep drive and encourage sleep to come more easily. Don\’t know the difference between sleepy and tired? Check out the \"Learn\" tab .Use these activities to help you stay up until your prescribed bedtime. If you are not sleepy at your prescribed bedtime, look at the \"Quiet Your Mind\" section for ways to help your mind and body relax. Remember never to stay up when sleepy if it could interfere with activities or responsibilities where sleepiness can be dangerous</string>
    <string name="s_SetUpYourSleepEnvironment">Set Up Your Sleep Environment</string>
    <string name="s_GotoBedOnlyWhenSleepy">Go to Bed Only When Sleepy</string>
    <string name="s_GetoutofBedWhenyoucantSleep">Get Out of Bed When You Can\'t Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_GetoutofBedatyourPrescribedTime">Get Out of Bed at Your Prescribed Time</string>
    <string name="s_SetCaffeineGoals">Set Caffeine Goals</string>
    <string name="s_34a">Incorporating new habits into your nighttime routine can help sleep come more easily. Use the following tools to shape your current schedule into one that leads to quality sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_34i">It is important to manage caffeine intake if you are having trouble sleeping. People who are having difficulty sleeping should drink no more than three 8-oz cups of caffeinated beverages per day, and avoid having any after lunch. If you would like to manage your caffeine intake, set a daily goal below:</string>
    <string name="s_ReducingCaffeine">Reducing Caffeine</string>
    <string name="s_NewSleepHabits">New Sleep Habits</string>
    <string name="s_DailyCaffeineDrinkLimit">Daily Caffeine Drink Limit</string>
    <string name="s_34f">Use the following checklist to make sure you have the optimum sleep environment. If it is not possible to adapt your environment to these guidelines, read about alternate possibilities.</string>
    <string name="s_LowNoiseLevel">Low Noise Level</string>
    <string name="s_Roomisdark">Room is dark</string>
    <string name="s_34h">Keeping a home environment that is consistent with good sleep habits is a key part of improving your sleep. Use the suggested adaptations when changing your environment is difficult.</string>
    <string name="s_Temperatureiscomfortable">Temperature is comfortable</string>
    <string name="s_Sleepisundisturbedbyothers">Sleep is undisturbed by others</string>
    <string name="s_Reservemybedforsleepsex">Reserve my bed for sleep/sex</string>
    <string name="s_Lownoiseleveltext">Noise from traffic or the outside environment can be difficult to control. If noise may be keeping you awake consider using a fan or white noise machine to make your bed area more conducive to sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_Roomisdarktext">Sometimes morning light, the full moon, or street lighting can interfere with getting a good night’s sleep. Consider changing window coverings if light may be an issue.</string>
    <string name="s_Temperatureiscomfortabletext">Feeling too warm or cold during the night can interfere with sleep. Consider layering sleep clothing and blankets so temperature is easier to adjust, or purchase a fan or space heater.</string>
    <string name="s_Sleepisundisturbedbyotherstext">Consider alternate sleep arrangements with partners and pets that will allow you the space and quiet you need.</string>
    <string name="s_Reservemybedforsleepsextext">If living in a dorm or studio makes reserving your bed for sleep and sex difficult, create another corner in your room for other activities. If you must use the bed for other activities try covering the bed with a day blanket (of a different color than your night blanket). When you are ready for sleep, remove the blanket. This will help cue your mind to associate your bed with sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_SleepEnvironment">Sleep Environment</string>
    <string name="s_slpy_text">If you are having trouble staying awake until your scheduled bedtime, see the Activities to Keep You Awake, below, for ideas on how to keep yourself up until it’s time for bed.  If an activity continues to work for you tap the star next to it to highlight it. </string>
    <string name="s_awake05">Call a friend</string>
    <string name="s_awake06">Do stretching exercises</string>
    <string name="s_awake03">Watch a mystery show</string>
    <string name="s_awake04">Write a long letter</string>
    <string name="s_awake01">Work on a project or hobby that you find interesting</string>
    <string name="s_awake02">Read a book that is hard to put down</string>
    <string name="s_awake07">Stand up and walk around</string>
    <string name="s_awake08">Do house chores</string>
    <string name="s_awake09">Listen to upbeat music (sing or hum along)</string>
    <string name="s_awake11">Watch a comedy show</string>
    <string name="s_awake10">Dance to upbeat music</string>
    <string name="s_awake13">Watch a comedy show</string>
    <string name="s_awake12">Stand up and walk around</string>
    <string name="s_awake15">Go outside (if it safe)</string>
    <string name="s_awake14">Turn on all the lights</string>
    <string name="s_awake17">Prepare meals for the rest of the week</string>
    <string name="s_awake16">Pack tomorrow’s lunch</string>
    <string name="s_awake18">Sort laundry</string>
    <string name="s_awake19">Organize computer files</string>
    <string name="s_awake20">Organize drawers/shelves</string>
    <string name="s_ActivitiesToKeepYouAwake">Activities To Keep You Awake</string>
    <string name="s_GotoBed">Go to Bed</string>
    <string name="s_GetoutofBed">Get out of Bed</string>
    <string name="s_34e1">Getting out of bed when you are having trouble sleeping helps prevent your mind from associating being awake with being in bed, which can help your sleep in the future. Use some of the activity ideas to keep yourself relaxed and occupied until you are very sleepy and ready to return to bed. When you get out of bed you should do things that are engaging but calming.</string>
    <string name="s_34e2">Getting out of bed in the morning at your prescribed time helps keep your sleep schedule consistent and prevents you from associating being in bed with being awake. Use these ideas for activities to help motivate you to start your day. Also consider setting an activity reminder that coincides with your prescribed wake up time.</string>
    <string name="s_ActivitiesfortheMiddleoftheNight">Activities for the Middle of the Night</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep04">Play solitaire online or with cards at home, as long as you are not too competitive about it</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep03">Sort out junk mail and bills (but don’t pay bills)</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep02">Update your address books or start one online or on paper</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep01">Look through catalogs</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep08">De-clutter your coffee table, dining room table, kitchen countertops or desk</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep07">Create a detailed menu for dinners</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep06">Make a grocery shopping list for the week</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep05">Catch up on your reading (as long as the reading materials can keep you awake)</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep09">Create a list of activities that you\’d enjoy doing on weekends and vacations</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep20">Read your kids\’ books- these are often very comforting and positive in their messages</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep14">Make a materials list for a project around the house </string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep15">Choose one or two drawers to clean out (in your desk, kitchen, bathroom)</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep12">Shop for holiday, wedding or birthday gifts online </string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep13">Read magazines or other light material</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep18">Jot down thoughts on a notepad for an assigned period of time. Use this exercise to help decrease nighttime thinking and worrying</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep19">Knit or do other crafts that you can stop working on when you feel sleepy</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep16">Watch infomercials, C-SPAN, The Weather Channel, or other repetitive television shows</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep17">Organize collections of CDs or DVDs and choose some to donate or sell if you no longer enjoy them</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep10">Work on photo albums or scrapbooks</string>
    <string name="s_CantSleep11">Fold clothes, put away clothes</string>
    <string name="s_MorningActivities">Morning Activities</string>
    <string name="s_GetOutofBedatYourPrescribedTime">Get Out of Bed at Your Prescribed Time</string>
    <string name="s_MorningActivitiestext">Having an activity to look forward to in the morning can help getting out of bed at the same time each day seem more doable. See Morning Activities, below, for ideas for things to do in the morning. If an activity continues to work for you, you may want to tap the star next to it to highlight it.  </string>
    <string name="s_GetOut02">Watch the sunrise</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut03">Take the dog for a walk</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut01">Meditate or Pray</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut06">Go to the grocery store or other stores that open early</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut07">Make lunch for yourself and for everyone else in the house</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut04">Read the newspaper or read the news online</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut05">Go to your gym or workout at home</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut08">Enjoy being able to get ready for work and kids ready for school without having to rush</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut09">Sort out some kids’ toys and choose things for Goodwill or a yard sale</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut10">Sort and start your laundry, or iron clothes for work</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut11">Start a budget for your family on a spreadsheet or in a notebook </string>
    <string name="s_GetOut12">Send emails to friends or check your work email</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut13">Shred or erase old computer disks, DVDs, etc. </string>
    <string name="s_GetOut14">Organize all of your bills, receipts, coupons and warranty information in a filing cabinet or folders</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut15">Get some of the preparation started for dinner dishes (marinating, chopping vegetables, and so on)</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut16">Make the bed and tidy up your bedroom </string>
    <string name="s_GetOut17">Open the curtains and blinds in the house</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut18">Sweep your sidewalk or steps, or shovel snow</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut19">Do some light gardening or water houseplants or those around your porch</string>
    <string name="s_GetOut20">Review your to-do list for the day or the week</string>
    <string name="s_35a">Relaxation exercises are opportunities to help your body learn to relax.  Try each of the exercises to determine which ones are the most appealing and useful.  </string>
    <string name="s_WindingDown">Winding Down</string>
    <string name="s_ChangeYourPerspective">Change Your Perspective</string>
    <string name="s_ScheduleWorryTime">Schedule Worry Time</string>
    <string name="s_BreathingTool">Breathing Tool</string>
    <string name="s_ProgressiveMuscleRelaxation">Progressive Muscle Relaxation</string>
    <string name="s_GuidedImageryForest">Guided Imagery: Forest</string>
    <string name="s_GuidedImageryCountryRoad">Guided Imagery: Country Road</string>
    <string name="s_GuidedImageryBeach">Guided Imagery: Beach</string>
    <string name="s_ObserveThoughtsCloudsintheSky">Observe Thoughts: Clouds in the Sky</string>
    <string name="s_ObserveSensationsBodyScan">Observe Sensations: Body Scan</string>
    <string name="s_35b">Relaxation is an integral part of being able to sleep. Use the tools in this section to encourage relaxation of the mind and body, so that sleep comes naturally.</string>
    <string name="s_WindDownTimetext">Having a wind-down time before you go to sleep can help relax your mind and body. See the Evening Activities below to explore some ideas for things to do during your buffer zone. If an activity continues to work for you, you may want to tap the star next to it to mark it as a favorite.  </string>
    <string name="s_EveningActivities">Evening Activities
</string>
    <string name="s_Wind21">Knit</string>
    <string name="s_Wind20">Floss</string>
    <string name="s_Wind10">Listen to slow, relaxing or instrumental music</string>
    <string name="s_Wind12">Organize collections - photos, old letters, books, or other items</string>
    <string name="s_Wind11">Gather old bills and statements and shred them</string>
    <string name="s_Wind14">Polish your shoes</string>
    <string name="s_Wind13">Catch up on laundry or folding clothes</string>
    <string name="s_Wind16">Write in your journal</string>
    <string name="s_Wind15">Iron or mend clothing</string>
    <string name="s_Wind18">Give yourself a pedicure, manicure, or facial</string>
    <string name="s_Wind17">Do some stretches to relax your muscles</string>
    <string name="s_Wind19">Sweep or mop the kitchen floor while no one else is there to walk on it</string>
    <string name="s_Wind08">Take the dog for a long walk</string>
    <string name="s_Wind09">Groom your pets</string>
    <string name="s_Wind06">Surf the internet (non-stressful topics only)  or do research for major purchases (cars, appliances, vacations)</string>
    <string name="s_Wind07">Watch movies or episodes of television shows that you haven\’t seen in a long time (no action films or thrillers)</string>
    <string name="s_Wind04">Take a bath or long shower</string>
    <string name="s_Wind02">Make your lunch for the next day</string>
    <string name="s_Wind03">Prepare dinner for the next day and store it in the refrigerator</string>
    <string name="s_Wind01">Choose clothes to wear the next day</string>
    <string name="sw_Wind05">Write thank you notes or short emails to friends</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep02">I will survive even if I don\'t sleep at all tonight.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep03">I\'ve done this before, so I know I can do it again.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep04">I don\'t have to feel comfortable all the time.  I am human.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep05">This is another challenge that I will figure out and face.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep06">I have been through this before and been just fine.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep07">One night of poor sleep is not the end of the world.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep08">This tossing and turning at night will pass.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep09">Although it feels like I will never get a good night’s sleep it may not be the case. Anticipating that I may not sleep well will likely make my sleep worse.  I have functioned well before even after not sleeping well.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep10">I have functioned poorly before even after I did sleep well</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep11">Although I am anticipating a poor night\'s sleep, it could be fine…I have slept well before.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep12">The body naturally regulates sleep; even if I miss some sleep I will be able to function.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep13">If I do not worry about sleep, having poor sleep one night will likely improve my sleep the next night.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma01">I have been through many hard things in my life and survived.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma02">Nightmares are disturbing, but they\'re not real. I am safe.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma03">I know I\'m in a safe place, even though my mind is telling me something else.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma04">I can feel my heart beating and my feet on the floor.  I am alive and okay.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma05">I have been through worse before and made it through safely.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma06">My body is reacting to a memory.  Right now I am safe.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma07">This situation is different than what happened to me and I\'m going to be fine.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma08">I am right here, right now.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma09">I am strong.  I am safe now.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma10">I am able to protect myself.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma11">This feeling will pass.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma12">I am in a safe place.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Trauma13">This feeling will pass.</string>
    <string name="s_Wind22">Quilt</string>
    <string name="s_Wind05">Write thank you notes or short emails to friends</string>
    <string name="s_Thought_Sleep01">I can tolerate this.</string>
    <string name="s_Thought">Thought</string>
    <string name="s_TryAnother">Try Another</string>
    <string name="s_ChangeYourPerspectivetext">Changing the way you think can change the way you feel and how well you sleep.  Concentrate on alternative thoughts to begin to feel better.</string>
    <string name="s_WorriedAboutSleep">Worried About Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_WorriedAboutTrauma">Worried About Trauma</string>
    <string name="s_Perspective">Perspective</string>
    <string name="s_35e2">The Change Your Perspective tool provides reminders that can help give you hope and confidence. We all have a constant stream of thoughts running through our minds—this is called self-talk.  Negative self-talk, like believing that things are terrible or that the worst is about to happen can stress your body and keep you on alert all the time. These positive self-talk reminders give you something you can hold on to; they can help you think more realistically, and may even help you manage situations more effectively.</string>
    <string name="s_35e1">Working some wind-down time into your sleep routine can help sleep come more easily. View the activity suggestions for ways to engage in calming activities that help prepare you for sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_35dhelp">Scheduling a worry time can help people gain some control over anxious thoughts that may be keeping them awake. Pick a daily time at which you can review the thoughts that may prevent you from falling asleep. Try not to pick a time too close to your bedtime, so that you have an opportunity to wind down afterwards.</string>
    <string name="s_WindingDowntext">One strategy that has been shown to be helpful for quieting anxious thoughts is scheduling a worry time. Although this may seem like the opposite of a useful goal for people struggling with anxiety, it actually can help get control over rumination. If you find yourself up at night worrying, try entering a scheduled day and time below that you can think about the issues that are on your mind.</string>
    <string name="s_35a16">For this exercise, find a comfortable and quiet place to sit, where you are unlikely to be disturbed. This mindfulness exercise will help you practice mindfulness of physical sensations. Please note that there will be pauses in the audio so you can practice without distraction. \n\nTime: About 9 minutes.</string>
    <string name="s_SelfGuided">Self Guided</string>
    <string name="s_AudioGuided">Audio Guided</string>
    <string name="s_35a15">For this exercise, find a comfortable and quiet place to sit, where you are unlikely to be disturbed. This mindfulness exercise will help you practice mindfulness of physical sensations. Please note that there will be pauses in the audio so you can practice without distraction. \n\nTime: About 7 minutes.</string>
    <string name="s_35a15help">Practice being mindful of your full range of sensations, thoughts, and experiences in the moment. Practice these mindfulness exercises with audio guidance, or on your own. Please do not do these exercises while driving or doing other work that requires your full attention.</string>
    <string name="s_35a16help">Practice being mindful of your full range of sensations, thoughts, and experiences in the moment. Practice these mindfulness exercises with audio guidance, or on your own. Please do not do these exercises while driving or doing other work that requires your full attention.</string>
    <string name="s_35a25self">Please read the following script through until you feel familiar with it, then follow the instructions on your own.\n\nStart this exercise by finding a comfortable position sitting or lying down. Take a few deep breaths—relax.\n\nImagine that you\’re looking up into the bright blue sky. Feel the sensation of the air - maybe a light wind passing by - and you can feel that air move across your skin.  Notice that there are large white puffy clouds that move from one side of the sky to the other.  Follow the large white clouds as they appear on one edge of your vision, move across the sky and then pass out of your vision on the other side.  And after one cloud make its movement across the sky then another cloud comes and does the same.  And they keep coming, one after another, moving across the sky.\n\nBegin becoming aware of the thoughts that are going through your mind.  Take whatever the first thought is that comes to your mind and see if you can take that thought and place it on one of the clouds and just let the cloud flow by.  Then do the same thing with the next thought that comes to your mind. You can also put sensations, feelings, or urges on clouds and let them flow by. You might choose to represent those thoughts or experiences as one word that you put on the cloud or it might be an image or some other way of representing whatever it is that you are experiencing.  There is no right or wrong way to do it.   Simply practice noticing whatever is there for you, in turn placing each one on a cloud and letting it move past.\n\nIf you get distracted or think that you can’t do this, put that thought on a cloud, watch it go by, and return to the process.  You might even have to do that over and over again.\n\nNotice one last thought or experience,   place it on a cloud and let the cloud trail by while you bring your awareness back here to this moment.  Notice any sensations in your body.  Notice the sensation of breathing. Take two more deep breaths and whenever you are ready you can open your eyes and return your awareness to your surroundings.</string>
    <string name="s_35a26self">Please read the following script through until you feel familiar with it, then follow the instructions on your own.\n\nStart this exercise by finding a comfortable position sitting or lying down. Take a few deep breaths—relax.\n\nNow bring your awareness to your fingers. Rub them together and notice their texture, temperature, and the sensations as they move.  Can you feel the indentations of your fingerprints? Take your time noticing all of this.
Now rest your fingers where they were before. What are they touching? What does that feel like? Is it soft? hard? What are its features and textures?  Really notice what you feel.\n\nNow bring attention to your hands and arms. What do they feel like? Relaxed? Heavy? Tense? Painful?  Try to observe these sensations, including uncomfortable ones, without judgment. \n\nNotice your toes now. Wiggle them and feel whatever is around and under them. How does it feel? Can you tell what it is just by feeling?\n\nNext, notice how your head is positioned. Is it upright? drooping? Is your neck turned in a particular direction? Simply notice this without trying to change it. Also note the sensations in your head and neck, including temperature, pain, and relaxation. Take your time noticing.
What about your face? Is your brow smooth or wrinkled up? How does it feel? Now notice your nose. Can you breathe freely? As you breathe, notice the sensations in your nose and lungs—expansion, tickling, warmth, or coolness. Then notice how your mouth is positioned? Is it pursed? Open? Closed? Is the inside of your mouth wet or dry? Just notice. Also, notice how your skin feels.  Is it dry? Itchy, tingling, hot or cool? Is there no sensation?\n\nNow notice your chest and belly. Place one hand on your chest and one on your belly. Can you feel your body breathing? What is that like? Are you breathing fast or slow? Is your breath going more into your belly or your chest? Just notice all these sensations.\n\nNext expand your attention to include your whole body. Where are you sitting or lying? Can you feel the back side of your body touching the chair or bed in places? Without moving, just observe your body’s position.\n\nWhen you are ready, look around the room and notice your surroundings, without judgment. When you are ready, stop this exercise and continue to relax.</string>
    <string name="s_35a25audio">Please listen to the audio and follow along with the exercise. </string>
    <string name="s_35a26audio">Please listen to the audio and follow along with the exercise. </string>
    <string name="s_PreventInsomnia">Prevent Insomnia</string>
    <string name="s_Feedback">Feedback</string>
    <string name="s_PreventInsomniatext">Difficulty sleeping can return in certain situations; this is normal.\n\nIf you find that your sleep is getting worse take the self-quiz below to see what areas you might be able to improve:\n\nWhich of these have you had trouble with?</string>
    <string name="s_Prevent01">I have trouble waking up and getting out of bed at my prescribed wake time. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent02">I have trouble going to bed only when I\'m sleepy and not before my prescribed bedtime. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent03">It is hard for me to get out of bed when I can\’t sleep. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent04">I have trouble creating a buffer zone to wind down before sleep. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent05">I worry in bed. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent06">I am having trouble limiting my caffeine use. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent07">I don\’t have a sleep environment that is quiet, dark and cool. </string>
    <string name="s_Prevent08">I can\'t relax enough for sleep </string>
    <string name="s_36b">Sleep is the result of a complex physiological system that is very sensitive to distress. This means that difficulty sleeping can return in certain situations. Use this tool to pinpoint ways to maintain good sleep when symptoms of insomnia return.</string>
    <string name="s_Submit">Submit</string>
    <string name="s_36c2">Based on these issues, try looking at the following tools:</string>
    <string name="s_36c3">When to Seek Help\n\nIf you notice new sleep-related problems, contact your doctor and schedule an appointment. Such problems can include:\n\n•	Loud snoring\n\n•	Stopping breathing, breathing pauses, gasping or snorting during sleep\n\n•	Falling asleep unintentionally or dozing during the day\n\n•	A creep-crawling sensation in your lower legs in the evening, along with an irresistible urge to move your legs to get rid of the feeling\n\n•	Very frequent leg jerking during your sleep\n\n•	Any other unusual new sleep experiences</string>
    <string name="s_36c1">Here are the items that might create problems for you:</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR01">Get Out of Bed at Your Prescribed Time</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR02">Go to Bed Only When Sleepy</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR03">Get Out of Bed When You Can\'t Sleep</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR04">Winding Down</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR05">Schedule Worry Time</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR06">Setting Caffeine Goals</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR07">Set Up Your Sleep Environment</string>
    <string name="s_ToolR08">Quiet Your Mind</string>
    <string name="s_35a12help">This exercise will guide you in imaging a pleasant scene in order to reduce stress and help you relax.  With this guided imagery you can relax your muscles and breathe more deeply while you focus on the relaxing scene in order to relax more deeply.</string>
    <string name="s_ForestImagery">Forest Imagery</string>
    <string name="s_RoadImagery">Road Imagery</string>
    <string name="s_BeachImagery">Beach Imagery</string>
    <string name="s_BeachText">You are about to be led through a relaxation exercise focused on visualizing something pleasant. This exercise takes about 4 minutes. It has accompanying audio, so you will have to find a quiet place or put on your headphones now.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest01">First, remove all distractions - let others know not to bother you.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest02">Make yourself comfortable, so that your thoughts are on the image and nothing else.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest03">Sit, or lie down, in a quiet, comfortable place.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest04">Mentally scan your body for tense muscles.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest05">If you find a muscle is tense, or clenched, relax it.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest06">During the imagery exercise, involve all of your senses in the image: sight, sound, smell, touch, and taste.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest07">Get completely focused.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest08">The more focused you are, the better.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest09">Close your eyes, or lower your gaze.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest10">Imagine that you are walking down a path, into a lush forest.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest11">As you walk along the path, you completely take in the sights, sounds, smells, and feel of the place.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest12">All around you are trees, grasses, mossy ground cover, and fragrant flowers.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest13">You hear the soothing sounds of birds chirping, and the wind as it gently blows through the treetops.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest14">You smell the rich dampness of the forest floor, the smells of moist vegetation and new growth.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest15">Through gaps in the treetops, you see the sun high in the cloudless blue sky.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest16">The sun is dispersed through the canopy of the treetops and filters down onto the forest floor, creating intricate patterns of light and shadow.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest17">With each breath you take in this place, you feel a deep sense of peace and relaxation.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest18">You soon come to a clearing.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest19">There are several flat rocks in the clearing surrounded by a soft moss.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest20">A small stream runs along the rocks.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest21">You lie back on one of the rocks, or on the cushiony moss, and put your feet into the cool water.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest22">You feel the warm sun and a gentle, light breeze through your hair and across your skin.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest23">The sparkling clear water rushes around the multi-colored rocks, making little whirlpools and eddies.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest24">You put your hand into the water and lift a handful to your lips.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest25">The water is cool and refreshing.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest26">You close your eyes and listen to the water trickling around the rocks. You bathe in the warm sun, and feel as though you\'re floating, relaxing deeper and deeper.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest27">You let yourself sink further into relaxation while continuing to be aware of the sights, smells, sounds, and feel of the forest around you.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest28">You allow yourself to let go of any concerns or worries, and to feel completely refreshed and rejuvenated in this place.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest29">When you\'re ready, imagine that you slowly get up and leave the clearing.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest30">As you walk back down the path through the forest, fully take in this place, and realize that you may return whenever you wish by the same path.</string>
    <string name="s_Forest31">Each time you enter this place, you will feel relaxed and at peace.</string>
    <string name="s_Play">Play</string>
    <string name="s_Road01">First, remove distractions - let others know not to bother you.</string>
    <string name="s_Road02">Make yourself comfortable, so that your thoughts are on the image and nothing else.</string>
    <string name="s_Road03">Sit, or lie down, in a quiet, comfortable place, then, mentally scan your body for tense muscles.</string>
    <string name="s_Road04">If you find a muscle is tense, or clenched, relax it.</string>
    <string name="s_Road05">During the imagery exercise, involve all of your senses in the image: sight, sound, smell, touch, and taste</string>
    <string name="s_Road06">Get completely focused.</string>
    <string name="s_Road07">The more focused you are, the better.</string>
    <string name="s_Road08">Imagine yourself walking along an old country road. The sun is warm on your back, the birds are singing, the air is calm and fragrant.</string>
    <string name="s_Road09">After a few steps, you come across an old gate.</string>
    <string name="s_Road10">The gate creaks as you open it and go through.</string>
    <string name="s_Road11">You find yourself in an overgrown garden, flowers growing where they have seeded themselves, vines climbing over a fallen tree, green grass, and shade trees.</string>
    <string name="s_Road12">Breathe deeply, smelling the flowers.</string>
    <string name="s_Road13">Listen to the birds and insects.</string>
    <string name="s_Road14">Feel the gentle breeze, warm against your skin.</string>
    <string name="s_Road15">You walk leisurely up a gentle slope behind the garden, and come to a wooded area, where the trees become denser</string>
    <string name="s_Road16">The sun is filtered through the leaves.</string>
    <string name="s_Road17">The air feels mild, and a bit cooler.</string>
    <string name="s_Road18">You become aware of the sound of a nearby brook.</string>
    <string name="s_Road19">You breathe deeply of the cool and fragrant air several times, and with each breath, you feel more relaxed.</string>
    <string name="s_Road20">Soon, you come upon the brook.</string>
    <string name="s_Road21">It\'s clear and clean as it tumbles over the rocks and some fallen logs.</string>
    <string name="s_Road22">You follow the path along the brook for a ways</string>
    <string name="s_Road23">The path takes you out into a sunlit clearing where you discover a small and picturesque waterfall.</string>
    <string name="s_Road24">There\'s a rainbow in the mist.</string>
    <string name="s_Road25">You find a comfortable place to sit for awhile, a perfect spot where you can feel completely relaxed.</string>
    <string name="s_Road26">You feel good, as you allow yourself to just enjoy the warmth and solitude of this peaceful place.</string>
    <string name="s_Road27">It\'s now time to return.</string>
    <string name="s_Road28">You walk back down the path, through the cool trees, out into the sun-drenched overgrown garden, one last smell of the flowers, and out the creaky gate.</string>
    <string name="s_Road29">You leave this secret retreat, for now, and return down the country road</string>
    <string name="s_Road30">Then, back to the room, slowly open your eyes, and remember, you can visit this place whenever you wish.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach01">First, remove distractions - let others know not to bother you.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach02">Make yourself comfortable, so that your thoughts are on the image and nothing else.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach03">Sit, or lie down, in a quiet, comfortable place.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach04">Then, mentally scan your body for tense muscles.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach05">If you find a muscle that\'s tense, or clenched, relax it.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach06">During the imagery exercise, involve all of your senses in the image: sight, sound, smell, touch, and taste.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach07">Get completely focused.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach08">The more focused you are, the better.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach09">Close your eyes, or lower your gaze.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach10">In your mind\'s eye, you see yourself descending down a long, narrow, wooden stairway, toward a beautiful, inviting beach.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach11">Your bare feet feel the rough, weathered step</string>
    <string name="s_Beach12">And with each step, you feel more and more tension gently melting away from your body.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach13">As you continue down the stairway, you notice the ocean is a deep shade of blue, with the fine, white crests of the waves sweeping towards the shore.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach14">You reach the end of the stairway, and step down, sinking into the warmth.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach15">As you soak in the warmth of the sun, a soothing sensation of relaxation gently melts through your entire body.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach16">The gentle sounds of the water lapping up onto the beach calm your mind, and allow you to feel even more relaxed.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach17">You begin walking slowly towards the edge of the water, and feel the warm sun on your face and shoulders.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach18">The salty smell of the ocean air invigorates you, and you take in a deep breath.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach19">Breathe slowly out, and feel more relaxed and refreshed.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach20">Finally, you reach the water\'s edge, and you gladly invite the little surges to flow over your toes and ankles.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach21">You watch the surges glide smoothly towards you, gently sweeping around your feet, and the trails of ocean water that flows slowly back out again.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach22">The cool water feels soft and comforting, as you enjoy a few moments, allowing yourself to gaze out on the far-reaching horizon.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach23">Overhead, you notice two birds gracefully soaring high above the ocean.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach24">And you can hear their soft cries becoming faint as they glide away.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach25">All of these sights, sounds, and sensations allow you to relax and let go, more and more.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach26">After a few moments, you begin slowly strolling down the beach, at the water\'s edge.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach27">You feel a warm, gentle breeze, pressing lightly against your back, and, with every step, you feel yourself relaxing, more and more.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach28">As you walk down the beach, you notice the details of sights and sounds around you, and the soothing sensations of the sun, the gentle breeze, and the sand below your feet.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach29">As you continue your leisurely walk down the beach, you notice a colorful beach chair, resting in a nice, peaceful spot, where the powdery, soft sand lies undisturbed.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach30">You approach this comfortable-looking beach chair, then you sit down, lie back, and settle in.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach31">You take in a long, deep breath, breathe slowly out, and feel even more relaxed and comfortable, resting in your chair.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach32">For a few moments more, let yourself enjoy the sights and sounds of this beautiful day on the beach.</string>
    <string name="s_Beach33">When you\'re ready, gently bring your attention back to the room, still letting yourself feel relaxed and comfortable, sitting where you are.</string>
    <string name="s_RoadText">You are about to be led through a relaxation exercise focused on visualizing something pleasant. This exercise takes about 4 minutes. It has accompanying audio, so you will have to find a quiet place or put on your headphones now</string>
    <string name="s_ForestText">You are about to be led through a relaxation exercise focused on visualizing something pleasant.  This exercise takes about 4 minutes.  It has accompanying audio so you will have to find a quiet place or put on your headphones now.</string>
    <string name="s_35a10help">This activity will guide you through a brief exercise in which you take slower, depper breaths to help you relax.  Taking slow, deep breaths helps you balance the carbon dioxide and orygen in your blood.  This calms your nervous system, creating a \"relaxation response.\"  Deep breathing exercises can help manage stress and insomnia, focus the mind and improve health.</string>
    <string name="s_35a10">Listen to the audio and follow along with the exercise.</string>
    <string name="s_35a11">You are about to be led through a progressive muscle relaxation exercise. You will progress through each of your major muscle groups, tensing and relaxing as you go. This exercise takes about 9 minutes. It has audio, so you will need to find a quiet place or put on your headphones now. Sit down in a comfortable chair or lay down. Do not do this exercise while driving.</string>
    <string name="s_35a11help">This exercise will guide you, either sitting comfortably or lying down, through tensing and relaxing a sequence of muscle groups.  This allows muscles to relax more deeply than usual.  This exercise can help decrease heart rate and blood pressure, slow breathing, decrease muscle tension and clear thinking\n\nThis exercise is also great because over time you can train yourself to really know what tense muscles feel like.  The, when you recognize that your muscles are tense or becoming tense you can immediately switch your muscles to the more relaxed state because you have trained yourself to know how relaxed muscles feel</string>
    <string name="s_muscle01">Please note that if you have injuries such as back pain or a knee injury, you should avoid tensing muscles that might affect that injury.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle02">To begin, close your eyes and take a deep breath into your belly.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle03">Then exhale with a sigh.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle04">Again, take a deep breath, and imagine clean air going down your throat, and filling your lungs, and then exhale with a sigh.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle05">Take another deep breath, and as you release it, think the word \"Relax\", silently to yourself.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle06">Allow your breath to be smooth and rhythmic, inhaling and exhaling at a pace that is comfortable for you.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle07">As you continue to breathe, continue to say the word \"Relax\" to yourself, slowly and calmly, each time you breathe out.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle08">As you do this, imagine that the tension throughout your body begins to melt away.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle09">To begin, clench both your fists, and bend your elbows, drawing your forearms and hands up towards your shoulders, tightening your biceps to do so.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle10">Hold the muscles in your hands and arms tight, and notice the sensations of pulling, discomfort, and tightness.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle11">Hold the tension, while you take a deep breath into your belly, and then slowly exhale, as you release the muscles of your hands and arms.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle12">Let your hands and fingers relax completely, and let your arms become limp at your side or in your lap.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle13">Feel the sensation of relaxation, as the tension drains away from your arms and hands, and allow the muscles to become looser and looser.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle14">You may notice that they feel lighter and warmer.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle15">Breathing in slowly, and out, thinking the word \"Relax\" each time you breathe out.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle16">Now bring your attention to your face, and tighten your forehead, the muscles around your eyes and your jaw, by squeezing your eyes tight, clenching your jaw, and wrinkling your forehead and nose</string>
    <string name="s_muscle17">Feel the wrinkling and pulling sensations across the forehead and the top of your head.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle18">Feel the tightness around your eyes and cheeks, and the tension in your jaw.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle19">Hold that tension, and take a deep breath into your belly, and then slowly exhale, as you let your face relax completely.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle20">Feel the muscles in your forehead becoming smooth and limp, the muscles of your cheeks and eyes softening, and your jaw relaxing. Let your lips part slightly, and let your jaw hang loose.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle21">Notice the tension melting away. Feel your muscles becoming softer, more relaxed, and feel the warmth and lightness that replaces the tension that was there before.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle22">Continue to breathe slowly and gently, thinking the word \"Relax\" each time you exhale.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle23">Tighten your shoulders by raising them up as if you were going to touch them to your ears, tensing without straining.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle24">Feel the tension in your shoulders radiating down into your back and up into your neck and the top of your back. Hold that. Notice those sensations and take a deep breath into your belly, and then slowly exhale as you relax your shoulders.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle25">Let your shoulders droop down and let your neck relax completely, feeling very relaxed</string>
    <string name="s_muscle26">Notice the contrast between the tightness you felt and the relaxation you feel now.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle27">Let your head relax, as if there\'s nothing holding it except the support behind it. Feel the sense of relaxation around your neck and shoulders as you let the tension drain away</string>
    <string name="s_muscle28">Continue to breathe slowly and deeply.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle29">Now bring your attention to your stomach.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle30">Tighten the muscles of your stomach by pulling your belly in towards your spine tightly.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle31">Hold that pose.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle32">Feel the sensation of the tension. Hold it while you are taking a deep breath, and then slowly exhale as you relax your muscles.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle33">Imagine a wave of relaxation spreading through your belly. Allow the muscles of your stomach to be soft and relaxed, letting go more and more.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle34">Notice the difference between the tension you felt and the relaxation you feel now. Let any remaining tension melt away, continuing to breathe gently in and out, feeling yourself become calmer and more relaxed.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle35">Now tighten your buttocks by squeezing them together, and at the same time squeeze the muscles of your thighs. You can lift your feet up to help tense your leg muscles. Notice the sensations of pulling, tightness, and constriction.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle36">Hold on to that tension, and focus on it, and take a deep breath. Then slowly exhale as you relax your buttocks and thighs.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle37">Allow your muscles to relax completely, and to let any tension drain away, melting away.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle38">Feel how the muscles of your hips and legs feel different now than when they did when you were clenching them.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle39">Really notice the difference. Continue to let go further and further, experiencing an even deeper relaxation, breathing in and out, slowly and gently, in and out.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle40">Now tighten the muscles of your calves and your feet as you flex your feet, pulling your toes towards you.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle41">Flex these muscles carefully to avoid a cramp.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle42">Continue to flex your feet, feeling the muscles of your calves, feet, and toes tighten and pull. Hold the tension for another second and take a deep breath. And now, slowly, exhale, release.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle43">As your muscles relax, notice how the sensations in your calves and feet change, perhaps feeling softer, or warmer, or lighter. Really notice how the sensations of tension are different from the sensations of relaxation you are now experiencing.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle44">With each breath, allow more tension to drain from your calves, relaxing more and more deeply. </string>
    <string name="s_muscle45">Continue to breathe slowly, thinking the word \"Relax\" each time you exhale, continuing to let any remaining tension drain away, breathing in, and out, in, and out.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle46">Relax, relax.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle47">Now that your whole body is feeling relaxed and comfortable, feel that sense of warmth and calmness spread over your whole body, continuing to breathe naturally, smoothly and steadily, letting the breath in and out, slowly and regularly, thinking the word \"relax\", every time you breathe out, breathing in, and out, in, and out.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle48">As you continue to breathe, imagine a wave of relaxation slowly spreading throughout your body.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle49">Starting at your head and gradually penetrating all of your muscles, all of the cells in your body, all the way down to your toes.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle50">Allow yourself to relax completely, continuing to breathe slowly and smoothly, sinking into that feeling of relaxation and noticing how it feels, so that you will be able to access it and recreate it later on your own.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle51">In a moment, I\'m going to count from 5 to 1. As I do, you will gradually feel more and more alert. When I get to 3, open your eyes, and when I get to 1, you will feel alert and refreshed and ready for the rest of your day.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle52">5, 4, beginning to shift your body, feeling a bit more awake now, 3, opening your eyes, 2, a bit more awake now, 1.</string>
    <string name="s_muscle53">Now you are feeling refreshed and alert, relaxed and ready for whatever is next. </string>
    <string name="s_btool01">To prepare, get in a comfortable position. Sitting would be best for now, so that you can practice as you listen and watch the demonstration</string>
    <string name="s_btool02">Later, when you practice, you can do this exercise sitting, standing up, or lying down - whatever works for you.</string>
    <string name="s_btool03">Although this exercise should be safe for almost anyone, if you have difficulty breathing, or feel out of breath, or begin to feel dizzy, nervous, or out of control, you can adjust your breathing pace, or go back to breathing normally</string>
    <string name="s_btool04">The goal is just to slow down a bit to allow your system to relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool05">Place one hand on your belly, and one on your chest</string>
    <string name="s_btool06">Breathe in by taking air deep into your belly - allow your belly to expand out while your shoulders and chest stay relaxed</string>
    <string name="s_btool07">Now breathe out, slowly, allowing the air you exhale to deflate your belly</string>
    <string name="s_btool08">Pause naturally</string>
    <string name="s_btool09">Breathe in, taking air deep into your belly. Allow your belly to expand; shoulders and chest stay relaxed</string>
    <string name="s_btool10">Now breathe out, slowly, but naturally</string>
    <string name="s_btool11">Breathe in, taking air deep into your belly</string>
    <string name="s_btool12">Think the number \"1\"</string>
    <string name="s_btool13">Now exhale all of the air, and think the word \"Relax\".</string>
    <string name="s_btool14">Breathe in, taking air deep into your belly, and think the number \"2\".</string>
    <string name="s_btool15">Now exhale all of the air, and think the word \"Relax\".</string>
    <string name="s_btool16">Breathe in - think the number \"3\".</string>
    <string name="s_btool17">Now exhale - think the word "Relax".</string>
    <string name="s_btool18">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool19">Think the number \"4\".</string>
    <string name="s_btool20">Now breathe out, slowly - think the word "Relax".</string>
    <string name="s_btool21">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool22">Five.</string>
    <string name="s_btool23">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool24">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool25">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool26">Six</string>
    <string name="s_btool27">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool28">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool29">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool30">Seven</string>
    <string name="s_btool31">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool32">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool33">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool34">Eight</string>
    <string name="s_btool35">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool36">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool37">Counting backwards now, breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool38">Eight</string>
    <string name="s_btool39">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool40">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool41">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool42">Seven</string>
    <string name="s_btool43">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool44">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool45">Breathe in slowly, deeply.</string>
    <string name="s_btool46">Think the number \"6\".</string>
    <string name="s_btool47">Breathe out slowly, all the way.</string>
    <string name="s_btool48">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool49">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool50">Five</string>
    <string name="s_btool51">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool52">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool53">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool54">Four</string>
    <string name="s_btool55">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool56">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool57">Breathe in - focus on your breath, and the number "3".</string>
    <string name="s_btool58">Breathe out, all the way - relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool59">Breathe in.</string>
    <string name="s_btool60">Two</string>
    <string name="s_btool61">Breathe Out.</string>
    <string name="s_btool62">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool63">Breathe in, for the last time</string>
    <string name="s_btool64">Think the number "1", and breathe out</string>
    <string name="s_btool65">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_btool66">Good Job</string>
    <string name="s_btool67">Even as you end this exercise, you can continue to allow your breathing to be deeper and slower. Take your time as you open your eyes, and bring your attention back to your surroundings.</string>
    <string name="s_NewEntry">New Entry</string>
    <string name="s_bScan01">Start this exercise by finding a comfortable position sitting in a chair, or lying on a bed or the floor</string>
    <string name="s_bScan02">Close your eyes and take a few deep breaths</string>
    <string name="s_bScan03">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_bScan04">Don\'t let yourself drift off to sleep during this exercise, but allow yourself to rest</string>
    <string name="s_bScan05">Now slowly bring your awareness to the tips of your fingers</string>
    <string name="s_bScan06">Feel your fingers</string>
    <string name="s_bScan07">Now, rub your fingertips together</string>
    <string name="s_bScan08">How do they feel?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan09">Can you feel the small indentations on that are your fingerprints?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan10">Take your time and try to feel them.</string>
    <string name="s_bScan11">What do they feel like?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan12">Are your fingertips raw from lots of work or are they smooth?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan13">How does it feel to rub them together?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan14">Notice the sensations.</string>
    <string name="s_bScan15">Now rest your fingers where they were before</string>
    <string name="s_bScan16">What are they touching?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan17">Are they resting on a blanket, on the arms of your chair, on your legs or stomach, or something else?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan18">What does that feel like?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan19">Is it soft or hard?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan20">Does it have any other distinguishing features or textures?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan21">Take the time to completely absorb the way these objects feel to your fingertips</string>
    <string name="s_bScan22">Now bring attention to your hands and arms. What do they feel like?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan23">Perhaps they are relaxed and heavy</string>
    <string name="s_bScan24">Perhaps they are tense from work or stress</string>
    <string name="s_bScan25">Either way is okay</string>
    <string name="s_bScan26">There is no need to judge; simply observe the feelings in your arms and hands</string>
    <string name="s_bScan27">Are there any aches or pains?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan28">Take note of these, but don\'t fixate on them. Simply notice the pain and move on</string>
    <string name="s_bScan29">Move your attention down to your toes now</string>
    <string name="s_bScan30">Wiggle them around a little. Are they in shoes or socks?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan31">Are they free to move about?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan32">Wiggle them and notice whatever is around or under them.</string>
    <string name="s_bScan33">Do you notice air, or the feeling of blankets or socks?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan34">Be aware of the experience</string>
    <string name="s_bScan35">Just notice the sensations as you bring your awareness to your feet</string>
    <string name="s_bScan36">Now shift your attention, and notice how your head is positioned</string>
    <string name="s_bScan37">Is it upright or tilted?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan38">Is your head turned in a particular direction?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan39">Simply notice your head\'s positioning without trying to change it</string>
    <string name="s_bScan40">Also notice any sensations that you are experiencing in your head or neck, such as tension or relaxation.</string>
    <string name="s_bScan41">Take your time noticing</string>
    <string name="s_bScan42">What about your face? How does your face feel?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan43">There are all kinds of sensations to explore here</string>
    <string name="s_bScan44">Think about your brow. Is it smooth and flat or is it wrinkled up with stress?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan45">Again, don\'t try to change it, just notice it</string>
    <string name="s_bScan46">Now bring awareness to your nose. Can you breathe freely?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan47">Take a few breaths in and out through your nose</string>
    <string name="s_bScan48">Can you feel air flowing into your nose?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan49">Is the air warm or cool?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan50">Pay attention to these feelings for a moment</string>
    <string name="s_bScan51">Then think about your mouth</string>
    <string name="s_bScan52">How is it positioned?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan53">Is it pursed? Open? Closed?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan54">What about the inside of your mouth? Is it wet or dry?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan55">Explore all of the sensations throughout your face</string>
    <string name="s_bScan56">Perhaps your skin feels dry, or you notice other sensations of itching, tingling, heaviness, heat, or coolness</string>
    <string name="s_bScan57">Perhaps there is no feeling at all. Just notice</string>
    <string name="s_bScan58">Now bring your attention to your chest and belly</string>
    <string name="s_bScan59">Place one hand on your chest and one hand on your belly</string>
    <string name="s_bScan60">Can you feel your body breathing? What is that like?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan61">Are you breathing fast or slow?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan62">Is your breath going more into your belly or your chest?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan63">Now breathe in through your nose and out through your mouth</string>
    <string name="s_bScan64">How does that feel?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan65">Now invert that pattern, breathing in through your mouth and out through your nose, and notice how that feels</string>
    <string name="s_bScan66">Now breathe naturally, just noticing the sensations</string>
    <string name="s_bScan67">Next place your hands wherever they were before and expand your attention to include your whole body</string>
    <string name="s_bScan68">Where are you sitting or lying?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan69">Can you feel the back side of your body touching the chair or bed in various places?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan70">Be mindful of the way your body is positioned</string>
    <string name="s_bScan71">There is no need to move, just observe</string>
    <string name="s_bScan72">Now, with your eyes still closed, imagine the room you\'re in</string>
    <string name="s_bScan73">Where are you positioned in the room?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan74">Do you have a sense of where the door is?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan75">What about the ceiling?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan76">Can you feel your body in the larger space?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan77">When you are ready, open your eyes and look around the room</string>
    <string name="s_bScan78">You can move if you wish</string>
    <string name="s_bScan79">Notice where the various pieces of furniture and decoration are</string>
    <string name="s_bScan80">What do they look like?</string>
    <string name="s_bScan81">You can spend as much time as you like investigating different aspects of the room</string>
    <string name="s_bScan82">Remember not to judge, just to notice</string>
    <string name="s_bScan83">Whenever you are ready, you can stop this exercise and continue with your day</string>
    <string name="s_Six">Six</string>
    <string name="s_Relax">Relax</string>
    <string name="s_Null"> </string>
    <string name="s_One">One</string>
    <string name="s_Two">Two</string>
    <string name="s_Three">Three</string>
    <string name="s_Four">Four</string>
    <string name="s_Five">5</string>
    <string name="s_Eight">Eight</string>
    <string name="s_Seven">Seven</string>
    <string name="s_NoEntries">No Entries</string>
    <string name="s_SDEDateHint">Enter today\'s date, even though some of the information you input will be from yesterday</string>
    <string name="s_EnterDate">Enter Date</string>
    <string name="s_SaveEntry">Save Entry</string>
    <string name="s_SDEDateWarn">It is often very difficult to remember sleep habits more than 24 hours later. If you were not able to enter data from previous days, it may be advisable to skip entering diary data for those days.</string>
    <string name="s_SDEDateError">Please choose today\’s date or a date in the past.</string>
    <string name="s_TNTQuestion">Did you nap or doze yesterday? </string>
    <string name="s_Minutes">Minutes</string>
    <string name="s_Hours">Hours</string>
    <string name="s_TNTInfo">Estimate the total amount of time you spent napping or dozing. For instance, if you napped twice, once for 30minutes and once for 60 minutes, and dozed for 10 minutes, you would answer \“1 hour 40 minutes.\”</string>
    <string name="s_BTInfo">Write the time that you got into your bed or your designated sleeping area. This may not be the time that you began \“trying\” to fall asleep.</string>
    <string name="s_SIATInfo">Record the time that you began \“trying\” to fall asleep.</string>
    <string name="s_SIATQuestion">What time did you try to go to sleep?</string>
    <string name="s_BTQuestion">What time did you get into bed yesterday?</string>
    <string name="s_TTSQuestion">How long did it take you to fall asleep?</string>
    <string name="s_TimesAwakeQuestion">How many times did you wake up, not counting your final awakening?</string>
    <string name="s_TAQuestion">In total, how long did these awakenings last?</string>
    <string name="s_TAInfo">What was the total time you were awake between the time you first fell asleep and your final awakening. For example, if you woke 3 times for 20 minutes, 35minutes, and 15 minutes, add them all up (20+35+15= 70 m or 1 hr and 10 m). This will likely be an estimate.</string>
    <string name="s_TTSInfo">Beginning at the time you started trying to go to sleep, record how long it
took you to fall asleep.  This will be an estimate.
</string>
    <string name="s_TimesAwakeInfo">How many times did you wake up between the time you first fell asleep and your final awakening?</string>
    <string name="s_WT_Info">Record the approximate time you got out of bed</string>
    <string name="s_WUT_Info">Record the last time you woke up in the morning.</string>
    <string name="s_SQQuestion">How would you rate the quality of your sleep?</string>
    <string name="s_CommentInfo">free to write anything that you would like to say that is relevant to your sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_EarlierQuestion2">How much earlier? </string>
    <string name="s_WUTQuestion">What time was your final awakening?</string>
    <string name="s_CommentQuestion">Comments:</string>
    <string name="s_EarlierQuestion">Did you wake up earlier than you desired? </string>
    <string name="s_WTQuestion">What time did you get out of bed for the day?</string>
    <string name="s_SQInfo">“Sleep Quality” is your sense of whether your sleep was  good or poor. Did you wake refreshed or not?</string>
    <string name="s_EarlierInfo">If you woke up or were awakened earlier than you planned, check yes. If you woke up at your planned time, check no. Write the number of minutes you woke up earlier than you had planned on waking up. For example, if you woke up 15 minutes before the alarm went off, record 15 minutes here.</string>
    <string name="s_CommentHint">Your comments here</string>
    <string name="s_SDEDateError2">Sleep Diary Entry for selected date already exists</string>
    <string name="s_WUTError">Error: The time you indicated you got out of bed is earlier than the time you indicated you woke up. Please enter the time you got out of bed for the final time.</string>
    <string name="s_SIATError">Error: The time you indicated you tried to sleep is earlier than the time you indicated you got into bed. Please enter the time you started trying to sleep after you had gotten into bed.</string>
    <string name="s_TIBError">The data you entered suggest that your total time in bed is a negative number. Please check your answers.</string>
    <string name="s_TSTError">The data you entered suggest that your calculated total sleep time is a negative number. Please check your answers.</string>
    <string name="s_TIBWarn">The data you entered suggest that you were in bed longer than 10 hours</string>
    <string name="s_TSTWarn">The data you entered suggest that you were in slept longer than 10 hours - is this correct?</string>
    <string name="s_TSTWarn2">The data you entered shows that you are getting less than five hours of sleep-this can be very difficult and can affect daily functioning. It is recommended that you see a provider to discuss ways to improve your sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_TTSWarn">You reported spending more than three hours awake or trying to get to sleep during the night. Is this correct? If you find yourself getting less than five hours of sleep on a typical night, contact your provider.</string>
    <string name="s_22d">Restricting the time you spend in bed can actually help you sleep better. If you have discussed specific times with your provider or would like to select your own bed times and wake times, choose \“Manually\” to enter the times that work best for you. If you would like the app to generate ideal bed times and wake times weekly, based on data from your sleep log, choose \“Automatically\”, then select the day you would like it to update each week. In order to calculate a sleep prescription the program needs data from your sleep diary for at least five nights in the past week.\n\nRemember, safety should always be considered when deciding how much time to allow for sleep. It is recommended you work with a provider to determine your best sleep prescription. If you have sleep apnea or if you find yourself very sleep during the day, visit the \"I Need Sleep\" section to take the questionnaire before determining a sleep prescription. Never restrict your sleep to the point where it affects your daily functioning.</string>
    <string name="s_22b">Restricting the time you spend in bed can actually help you sleep better. If you have discussed specific times with your provider or would like to select your own bed times and wake times, choose “Manually” to enter the times that work best for you. If you would like the app to generate ideal bed times and wake times weekly, based on data from your sleep log, choose “Automatically”, then select the day you would like it to update each week. In order to calculate a sleep prescription the program needs data from your sleep diary for at least five nights in the past week.  Your sleep efficiency shows the percentage of time in bed that you spend sleeping; increase this number to improve your sleep. </string>
    <string name="s_22a">Here you can update your prescribed bedtime and wake time, which can help you decide how long to spend in bed for sleep. Always consider your safety first when working to change your sleep habits. </string>
    <string name="s_22f">Restricting the time you spend in bed can actually help you sleep better. If you have discussed specific times with your provider or would like to select your own bed times and wake times, choose \“Manually\” to enter the times that work best for you. If you would like the app to generate ideal bed times and wake times weekly, based on data from your sleep log, choose \“Automatically\”, then select the day you would like it to update each week. In order to calculate a sleep prescription the program needs data from your sleep diary for at least five nights in the past week.\n\nRemember, safety should always be considered when deciding how much time to allow for sleep. It is recommended you work with a provider to determine your best sleep prescription. If you have sleep apnea or if you find yourself very sleep during the day, visit the \"I Need Sleep\" section to take the questionnaire before determining a sleep prescription. Never restrict your sleep to the point where it affects your daily functioning.</string>
    <string name="s_UpdateSleepPrescriptionNow">Update Sleep Prescription Now</string>
    <string name="s_Manually">Manually</string>
    <string name="s_Automatically">Automatically</string>
    <string name="s_UpdateError">The program was unable to update your sleep prescription due to insufficient information from your sleep diaries. Complete at least five diaries per week so the program can generate a sleep prescription. It is best to work collaboratively with a provider to decide on a sleep prescription.</string>
    <string name="s_WhatIsYourPrescribedWaketime">What is your prescribed wake time?</string>
    <string name="s_WhatIsYourPrescribedBedtime">What is your prescribed bedtime?</string>
    <string name="s_ManWakeInfo">Choose a wake up time that works for your schedule. </string>
    <string name="s_ManBedInfo"> Choose a bedtime that works for your schedule. </string>
    <string name="s_eula10b">NATIONAL CENTER FOR TELEHEALTH AND TECHNOLOGY (T2)\n\nUNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF VETERANS AFFAIRS (\"VA\")\n\nSOFTWARE END USER LICENSE AGREEMENT\n\nBy agreeing to have any of T2/VA\’s software products installed on to your device and by subsequent use of the Licensed Software, you agree to comply with the terms of this general End User License Agreement (\'EULA\') where no specific agreement is in place between T2/VA and the user of the software. If you do not agree to the terms of this EULA, do not install or use the Licensed Software but uninstall it from your device. This EULA applies to any upgrades and supplements to the original Licensed Software provided and is referred to on your opening screen.\n\nThe Licensed Software is owned by T2 a division of the US Defense Centers of Excellence (DCOE) and the United States Department of Defense (DOD)and the VA. The Licensed Software is licensed, not sold, only on the terms of this EULA. Acceptance and installation of the software indicates your acceptance of the terms and conditions of this EULA.\n\nUpon installation of the Licensed Software, you will acquire the right to use the Licensed Software, directly from T2/VA. You assume responsibility for the selection of the program to achieve your intended results, and for the installation, use and results obtained from the Licensed Software.\n\nT2/VA and you acknowledge that this Agreement is concluded between T2/VA and you only, and not with Apple. T2/VA is solely responsible for the Licensed Software and its content.\n\nIn consideration of your acceptance of the terms and conditions contained in this EULA, T2/VA grants you a non-exclusive license to use the Licensed Software and the associated documentation for your own needs on one device. You are not licensed to rent, lease, transfer, or distribute the Licensed Software.\n\nTitle to the Licensed Software, including media and documentation, remain with T2/VA. You may not copy, reproduce or make data transmissions, in whole or in part, except as is necessary for back-up or archival purposes. You may not reverse engineer, translate, disassemble, decompile the Licensed Software or create similar software in whole or in part.\n\nThe license is effective upon acceptance and installation of the Licensed Software and shall continue until terminated. You may terminate it at any time by uninstalling the Licensed Software. T2/VA has the right to terminate this Agreement if you fail to comply with any term or condition of this EULA. Upon termination you shall stop all use of the Software and uninstall the Licensed Software.\n\nConfidentiality obligations pertaining to the Licensed Software will survive any termination of this EULA, to include the application, design, and functionality.\n\nThis Licensed Software is distributed AS IS, in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranties of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.\n\nIn no event will T2/VA be liable for any damages, including those for loss of data, loss of use, or indirect, special, incidental or consequential damages in any way related to or arising out of the use of the Licensed Software, whether based upon warranty, contract, or otherwise, whether or not injury was sustained by persons or property or otherwise, and whether or not loss was sustained from, or arose out of, use of Licensed Software . You agree to waive any and all claims against the U.S. Government, T2, VA, its contractors, their subcontractors, and shall indemnify and hold harmless the U.S. Government, its contractors, and their subcontractors for any damage that you may incur from your use of the Licensed Software.\n\nT2/VA shall be neither liable nor responsible for any maintenance or updating of the provided Licensed Software, nor for correction of any errors in the Licensed Software.\n\nThis Agreement shall be construed and enforced in accordance with federal law and each party agrees to be subject to those relevant laws for all purposes.\n\nIt is understood and acknowledged that T2/VA has the absolute right to obtain injunctive relief to protect T2\'s/VA\'s proprietary rights.\n\nBy using the Licensed Software, you further agree that this is the complete and exclusive statement of the Agreement which supersedes any proposal or prior agreement, oral or written, and any other communications relating to the subject matter of this EULA.\n\nIf any provision of this Agreement is held to be invalid or unenforceable the remaining provisions will not be affected.\n\nFor statistical purposes T2/VA collects anonymous usage data and sends it to a data provider. By accepting this agreement, it is understood that this feature can be disabled through the settings screen at any time.\n\nPRIVACY NOTICE: No individually identifiable data is transferred or transmitted to T2/VA in any way through the use of the Licensed Software. All individually identifiable data entered by you remains your sole property and will not be accessed by VA without your further express consent. You also acknowledge that it is your sole responsibility to protect and otherwise secure any information captured and stored by the software once installed on your device.\n\nDISCLAIMER: The content of this application is intended for use only as an informative tool. It is not, is not intended to be, and should not be used in any way as a substitute for professional medical advice or training. The accuracy of the information provided is not guaranteed. You acknowledge in initiating this application that the information is not meant to diagnose a health condition or disease and is not meant to develop a health treatment plan. If you are in an emergency or life-threatening medical situation, seek medical assistance immediately. Dial emergency number (911 in the USA) for emergency medical services.\n\nExternal Links: The appearance of external hyperlinks does not constitute endorsement by the United States Department of Defense or United States Department of Veterans Affairs of the linked websites, or the information, products or services contain therein. The United States Department of Defense and Department of Veterans Affiars does not exercise any editorial control over the information you may find at these locations. All links are provided consistent with the stated purpose of these DoD/VA websites.
</string>
    <string name="s_UpdateError2">Bedtime must be entered to update sleep prescription</string>
    <string name="s_UpdateError3">Waketime must be entered to update sleep prescription</string>
    <string name="s_UpdatePrescription">Update Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_WTError">Wake time is earlier than bed time</string>
    <string name="s_Updateautomaticallyeachweekon">Update automatically each week on:</string>
    <string name="s_20b">Use this section to update your personalized sleep prescription, complete your daily sleep diary, assess your sleep need and create reminders to help you stick to a sleep schedule.</string>
    <string name="s_Whatisyourdesiredwakeuptime">What is your desired wake up time?</string>
    <string name="s_AWTInfo">Choose a wake up time that works for your schedule. Your sleep prescription will use that time to select an ideal bedtime. </string>
    <string name="s_snq09a">Based on your scores, it does not seem necessary to change your sleep prescription at this time. However, if you are notice becoming extremely sleepy or having difficulty functioning during the day, discuss changing your sleep prescription with your provider. If your sleep efficiency is below 80%, it is recommended that you contact a provider.</string>
    <string name="s_snq09b">It has been less than a week since you last took the self-assessment. The questions are designed to assess your symptoms over time, so it is not helpful to take it more than once a week. Based on your current scores, it does not seem necessary to change your sleep prescription at this time. If you are notice becoming extremely sleepy or having difficulty functioning during the day, discuss changing your sleep prescription with your provider.  Try taking the assessment after a week or more to see if your sleep need has changed. Remember to never restrict sleep to the point where it could affect your daily functioning.</string>
    <string name="s_snq1012b">It has been less than a week since you last took the self-assessment. The questions are designed to assess your symptoms over time, so it is not helpful to take it more than once a week. Based on your current scores you may be having some issues with daytime sleepiness. Try taking the assessment after a week or more to see if your sleep need has changed. If you continue to have issues with daytime sleepiness, consider going to bed 15 minutes earlier. Remember to never restrict sleep to the point where it could affect your daily functioning</string>
    <string name="s_snq1012a">Based on your scores you may be having some issues with daytime sleepiness. Consider adding  15 minutes to your sleep prescription. Make sure to discuss these changes with your provider. Also let him or her know if you continue to notice becoming extremely sleepy or having difficulty functioning during the day. If your sleep efficiency is below 80%, it is recommended that you contact a provider as soon as possible.</string>
    <string name="s_snq13gb">It has been less than a week since you last took the self-assessment. The questions are designed to assess your symptoms over time, so it is not helpful to take it more than once a week. Based on your current scores, it seems that you are struggling with daytime sleepiness. Try taking the assessment after a week or more to see if your sleep need has changed.If you continue to struggle with daytime sleepiness, consider going to bed 30 minutes earlier. If your sleep efficiency is below 80%, it is recommended that you contact a provider as soon as possible. Remember to never restrict sleep to the point where it could affect your daily functioning</string>
    <string name="s_snq13ga">Based on your scores it seems that you are struggling with daytime sleepiness. Consider going to bed 30 minutes earlier.  Also let your provider know if you continue to notice becoming extremely sleepy or having difficulty functioning during the day. If your sleep efficiency is below 80%, it is recommended that you contact a provider as soon as possible. Remember, safety should always come first when working to modify your sleep habits.</string>
    <string name="s_23b">One part of CBT-i is using a \“sleep prescription\”, which gives people set times to get into bed and get out of bed. This has been shown to help people get deeper, more satisfying sleep.\n\nThis may be uncomfortable at first, however, because you may notice that you are spending less time in bed than you are used to. This questionnaire assesses your sleep need, to see if your sleep prescription should be changed.\n\nAlways check in with your provider about making changes to your sleep schedule. Make sure to be careful about how much you restrict your sleep. Operating on not enough sleep can be dangerous - safety should always come first when trying to change your sleeping habits.
</string>
    <string name="s_23a">This assessment is called the sleep need questionnaire.  This quiz can give you some valuable information about whether you and your provider should consider increasing your time in Bed.  However, remember to speak to a provider if you find yourself becoming very sleepy.  \n\nSince this quiz is designed to show your change over time related to your sleeping habits it is recommended that you take it no more than once a week</string>
    <string name="s_StartQuestionaire">Start Questionnaire</string>
    <string name="s_Add30">Add 30 minutes to Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_Add15">Add 15 minutes to Prescription</string>
    <string name="s_Done">Done</string>
    <string name="s_snq1">Question 1\nDid you feel tired or fatigued during the day or evening?</string>
    <string name="s_snq2">Question 2\nWere you sleepy or drowsy during the day or evening?</string>
    <string name="s_snq3">Question 3\nDid you take any naps or fall asleep briefly during the day or evening?</string>
    <string name="s_snq4">Question 4\nDid you feel you had been getting an adequate amount of sleep?</string>
    <string name="s_Next">Next Question</string>
    <string name="s_SleepData">Sleep Data</string>
    <string name="s_SeeaProvider">See a Provider</string>
    <string name="s_USP1">Based on the data you entered this week, your sleep efficiency is low. It is recommended that you make an appointment as soon as possible to see a provider to discuss ways to improve your sleep.</string>
    <string name="s_USP2">It is recommended that you see a provider to discuss adjusting your sleep prescription.</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ1">Please rate the severity of  the difficulty you had falling asleep in the past week:</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ10">None</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ11">Mild</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ12">Moderate</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ13">Severe</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ14">Very Severe</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ2">Please rate the severity of the difficulty you had staying asleep in the past week:</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ3">Please rate the severity of the problems with waking up too early you had  in the past week:</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ4">How SATISFIED/DISSATISFIED are you with your CURRENT sleep pattern?</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ40">Very Satisfied</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ41">Satisfied</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ42">Moderately Satisfied</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ43">Dissatisfied</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ44">Very Dissatisfied</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ5">How NOTICEABLE to others do you think your sleep problem is in terms of impairing the quality of your life? </string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ50">Not at all Noticeable</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ51">A Little</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ52">Somewhat</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ53">Much</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ54">Very Much Noticeable</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ6">How WORRIED/DISTRESSED are you about your current sleep problem? </string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ60">Not at all Worried</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ61">A Little</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ62">Somewhat</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ63">Much</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ64">Very Much Worried</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ7">To what extent do you consider your sleep problem to INTERFERE with your daily functioning (e.g. daytime fatigue, mood, ability to function at work/daily chores, concentration, memory, mood, etc.) CURRENTLY? </string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ70">Not at all Interfering</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ71">A Little</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ72">Somewhat</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ73">Much</string>
    <string name="s_ISIQ74">Very Much Interfering</string>
    <string name="s_ISITitle">Question %d of 7</string>
    <string name="s_ISI2">Are you currently working on your sleep with a healthcare provider?</string>
    <string name="s_ISI1">This self-assessment, the Insomnia Severity Index, cannot tell you if you have insomnia, but can give you some valuable information about your sleep symptoms.  If you are currently working with a sleep therapist, sharing the results of this assessment with him or her may help with your care. </string>
    <string name="s_ISIError">It has been less than a week since you last took the self-assessment.  The questions are designed to assess your symptoms since the last time you answered, so it is generally not helpful to take it more than once a week.</string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeed1">Your score suggests that you do not have symptoms meeting criteria for insomnia at this time. \n\nHowever, if you are feeling stressed,  make an appointment with a healthcare professional.  A professional will be able to help you understand what is going on and provide ways to deal with stress.  
    </string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeed2">You are reporting a number of sleep problems, similar to people who have been diagnosed with insomnia. If you continue to have these kinds of sleep problems over the next several weeks, you should talk with a trained health care provider.  Seeking help will be especially important if you think that you may have other problems which can interfere with sleep, such as depression, substance abuse, PTSD or anxiety.  This app can help you learn effective strategies for improving your sleep and allows you to keep track of how well you’re sleeping over time.  Take this assessment again in four weeks so you can keep an eye on your symptoms.</string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeed3">Your score is still within the normal range.\n\nHowever, this assessment will not pick up other problems that can be related to life stress such as depression, substance abuse, and anxiety.\n\nIf you are feeling stressed make an appointment with a healthcare professional, regardless of the outcome of this assessment.  A professional will be able to help you understand what is going on and provide ways to deal with stress. 
    </string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeed4">The sleep problems that you are reporting do not suggest insomnia.  Your score is an improvement over your previous scores on this assessment.  Answer the sleep questions again in four weeks so you can keep an eye on your symptoms.  If you continue to use this app to support good sleep habits, you may find that you will continue to sleep well.  However, don’t be alarmed if minor sleep difficulties occur once in a while. It’s not unusual to have occasional sleep problems, especially during times of increased stress.  
If you are feeling very stressed make an appointment with a healthcare professional, regardless of the outcome of this assessment.  A professional will be able to help you understand what is going on and what you can do to deal with stress.
    </string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeed5">You are continuing to report a number of sleep problems, similar to people who have been diagnosed with insomnia.   Since you are continuing to have these kinds of sleep problems, you should talk with a trained health care provider.  Seeking help will be especially important if you think that you may have other problems which can interfere with sleep, such as depression, substance abuse, PTSD or anxiety.  Share the results of this assessment with your health care provider.  Take this assessment again in four weeks so you can keep an eye on your symptoms and try to include the information and tools in this app in your bedtime routine.</string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeed6">You are reporting a number of sleep problems which are similar to people who have been diagnosed with insomnia.  Your sleep may have gotten worse since you last took the assessment.   If you continue to have these kinds of sleep problems over the next several weeks, you should talk with a trained health care provider.  Seeking help will be especially important if you think that you may have other problems which can interfere with sleep, such as depression, substance abuse, PTSD or anxiety. While there is no substitute for professional face-to-face care, this app can help you learn effective strategies for improving your sleep.  Take this assessment again in four weeks so you can keep an eye on your symptom picture.  </string>
    <string name="s_TakeAssessmentNow">Take Assessment Now</string>
    <string name="s_Off">Off</string>
    <string name="s_Yes">Yes</string>
    <string name="s_On">On</string>
    <string name="s_No">No</string>
    <string name="s_NextQuestion">Next Question</string>
    <string name="s_33a">You can track your symptoms by scheduling times to take the assessment in the future. It is normal for your symptoms to change a bit from day to day.  It is most important to look for a trend over time.  So, you should not take this assessment more than once per week. In most cases we suggest one time per month. This will help you see if your symptoms are getting better, worse, or staying the same. \n\nWould you like to set up a follow-up assessment now? If you are currently working with a provider we recommend you complete the ISI weekly.
</string>
    <string name="s_NoData">No Data</string>
    <string name="s_ISIFeedProv">Your provider will explain these results to you at your next session.</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score">Your total ISI Assessment Score is %d</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score01">Difficulty falling asleep? Score %d</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score02">Difficulty staying asleep? Score %d</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score03">Problem waking up too early? Score %d</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score04">Satisfaction with your current sleep pattern? Score %d</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score05">How noticeable to others do you think your sleep problem is in terms of impairing the quality of your life? Score %d"</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score06">Distress about your current sleep problem? Score %d</string>
    <string name="s_ISI_Score07">Sleep problem to interfere with your daily functioning? Score %d</string>
    <string name="s_ScheduleNextAssessment">Schedule Next Assessment</string>
    <string name="s_31g">It has been less than a week since you last took the self-assessment. The questions are designed to assess your symptoms over time, so it is not helpful to take it more than once a week.</string>
    <string name="s_21j">Here is your sleep data for the past 24 hours</string>
    <string formatted="false" name="s_TotalTimeInBed">Total Time In Bed  %dh:%02dm</string>
    <string formatted="false" name="s_TotalTimeAsleep">Total Time Asleep  %dh:%02dm</string>
    <string formatted="false" name="s_SleepEfficiency">Sleep Efficiency %d</string>
    <string name="s_Never">Never</string>
    <string name="s_Always">Always</string>
    <string name="s_Sometimes">Sometimes</string>
    <string name="s_Rarely">Rarely</string>
    <string name="s_Frequently">Frequently</string>
    <string name="s_34c1">Getting out of bed to do some relaxing activities when you can\’t sleep can help your body associate your bed with sleep.\n\nSee the Activities for the Middle of the Night below for ideas for things to do when you are having trouble sleeping.  If an activity continues to work for you tap the star next to it to highlight it.
</string>
    <string name="s_ClearHistory">Clear History</string>
    <string name="s_ShrowAssessmentDetails">Show Assessment Details</string>
    <string name="s_History">History</string>
    <string name="s_Cancel">Cancel</string>
    <string name="s_32c">You won\'t be able to compare new assessment results with your earlier results.  Are you sure you want to clear your assessment history?</string>
    <string name="s_32cTitle">Clear History?</string>
    <string name="s_32d">Once you take the assessment your results will show up here as a graph. Remember, no one will see your results other than you (your sleep therapist will be able to see the results if you decide to share them). This is an opportunity to get feedback on how severe your symptoms are, and if you are getting better or worse over time.   </string>
    <string name="s_AllAssessments">All Assessments</string>
    <string name="s_32f">Touch an item to view Assessment responses to specific questions.</string>
    <string name="s_Score">Score: </string>
    <string name="s_TooEarly">Too Early</string>
    <string name="s_OK">OK</string>
    <string name="s_Dismiss">Dismiss</string>
    <string name="s_Launch">Launch</string>
    <string name="s_bodyscan">Body Scan</string>
    <string name="s_cloudsinthesky">Clouds in the Sky</string>
</resources>
